Finding Aid for Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan Records 1911-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Publications, 1965-2006
  Brochures, newsletters, and pamphlets published between 1965 and 2006 comprise the Publications series. These materials were published by PPMM to describe the organization's programs and services. Newsletters are an excellent source of compiled information about the activities of PPMM at specific points in time.
  - Brochures and Flyers (Box 6)
  - Michigan's Choice and Voter's Guides, 2004-2006 (Box 6)
    (Planned Parenthood Advocates of Michigan)
  - Michigan's Voice, 2003-2006 (Box 6)
    (Planned Parenthood Affiliates of Michigan)
  - News and Views, 1987-1988 (Box 6)
  - Newsletters, 1965-1983 (Box 6)
    (Washtenaw County League for Planned Parenthood)
  - Newsletters, 1984-1987 (Box 6)
    (Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan)
  - Pamphlets (Box 6)
  - Plan Ahead, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
- Topical Files, 1911-1995
  Information collected by PPMM for informational purposes comprises the Topical Files series and includes documents produced between 1911 and 1995. Information on various topics including pro-choice religious organizations, population control, and studies relating to family planning and birth control were collected by PPMM. Of particular note are two early family planning pamphlets by Margaret Sanger and Douglas Neal.
  - Abortion History Project (Box 6)
  - Adoption, 1985-1987 (Box 6)
  - Catholics & Choice, 1981-1995; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Catholics for a Free Choice, 1982-1987; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Clergy and Choice, 1986-1992 (Box 6)
  - Clinton's Health Care Reform (Box 7)
  - Education Center, 1976 (Box 7)
  - Family Planning and Health, 1990-1991 (Box 7)
  - Gifts, 1973-1976 (Box 7)
  - Intra-uterine Contraceptive Device Study, 1962-1965 (Box 7)
  - Jane Schmidt, 1952-1959 (Box 7)
  - Margaret Sanger Day, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Health Rights Council, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Association for School Age Parents, 1970-1975 (Box 7)
  - Pamphlets on Birth Control by Margaret Sanger and Douglas Neal, 1911-1927 (Box 7)
  - Pamphlets on Miscellaneous Topics (Box 7)
  - People's Campaign for Choice, 1987 (Box 7)
  - Population Control Pamphlets (Box 7)
  - Population Planning, 1952-1978 (Box 7)
  - Population Planning Pamphlets (Box 7)
  - Population policy for the State of Michigan, 1973 (Box 7)
  - Pro-Choice Michigan, 1986 (Box 7)
  - Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights, 1987-1991 (Box 7)
  - Religious Organizations, 1986 (Box 7)
  - Reports, 1952-1969; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Reproductive Rights Litigation, 1989-1990 (Box 7)
  - Sexuality, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Silent Scream Forum, 1985 (Box 7)
  - Sterilization, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Student Papers, 1970 (Box 7)
  - Venereal Disease, 1973-1974 (Box 7)
  - Women's Issues, 1972-1974 (Box 7)
- Individuals' Files, 1938-1992
  The series entitled Individuals' Files contains records created by specific staff and board members of PPMM. This series includes files of Betty Ann Duff, who served as Executive Director from 1965 to 1969 and as Board President in 1977-1978; Deborah Oakley, a member of Board who also served on the Executive Committee in the 1970s; Nedra Otis, who was involved in the 1972 abortion law reform effort; and Molly Prendergast, who was Board President from 1969 to 1971. These records date from the 1970s and the 1990s, with a small amount of historical material dating from the late 1930s to the 1950s to be found among Deborah Oakley's files. They span a wide range of topics and complement the documents found in the other series.
  - Betty Ann Duff
    - Annual Meetings, 1988-1989 (Box 7)
    - Annual Reports, 1978-1991 (Box 7)
    - Capital Campaign, 1984 (Box 7)
    - Development Committee, 1988-1991 (Box 7)
    - Fashion Show Fund-raiser Committee, 1990-1991 (Box 7)
    - Health Emergency Loan Program Campaign, 1990-1991 (Box 7)
    - History, 1987 (Box 7)
    - Long Range Planning, 1988-1991 (Box 7)
    - Margaret Sanger Society, 1987-1991 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1990-1991 (Box 7)
    - Nominating Committee, 1990-1991 (Box 7)
    - Planned Giving Committee, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Public Affairs/Legislative Updates, 1990-1992 (Box 7)
  - Deborah Oakley
    - Notebook, 1970-1974; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Minutes and Reports, 1977-1978; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Miscellanea, 1938-1975 (Box 8)
  - Nedra Otis, 1971-1972; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Molly Prendergast, 1971-1975; 2 folders (Box 8)
- Visual Materials, 1960-2005
  The Visual Materials series comprises black-and-white and color photographs taken between the 1960s and 2005. The photographs document programs and special events hosted by PPMM. Included are photographs of staff and volunteers working in clinics and participating in pro-choice events and demonstrations, and portraits of the organizations' executives and board members. There are also interior and exterior shots of some clinic facilities, and a number of images of anti-abortion protestors, mostly taken outside the Ann Arbor Planned Parenthood clinic and administrative offices. This series also includes a 1989 videotape relating to Operation Rescue, and a 1994 video of two advertising spots for the Lansing and Jackson clinics.
  - Photographs
    - Annual Dinner, 1967 (Box 8)
    - Anti-Abortion Demonstrations and Counter-Demonstrations, 2 envelopes (Box 8)
    - Clinic (Box 8)
    - Clinic Staff and Anti-Abortion Protestors, 2005 (Box 8)
    - Early Clinic (Box 8)
    - Executive portraits, 1966-2005 (Box 8)
    - "Face of Pro-Choice,", 1992 (Box 8)
    - Jackson Clinic Staff and "Teen Talk" Session, circa 1990s (Box 8)
    - Legislative Luncheon, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Meetings, 1978-1979 (Box 8)
    - Meetings and Events, 1963-1964 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Negatives (Box 8)
    - North Main Street Building and Facilities (Box 8)
    - Peer Educators, 1986-1993 (Box 8)
    - Photo Album (Box 8)
    - Planned Parenthood Activities (Box 8)
    - Pro-Choice Demonstrations, Events, and Exhibits (Box 8)
    - Staff, 1960-1974; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Staff and Volunteer Groups (Box 8)
    - Staff and Volunteers (Box 8)
    - Teen Clinic, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Ypsilanti Clinic, 1975 (Box 8)
  - Negatives
    - Staff and Clinic (Box 8)
  - Slides
    - Jackson Clinic Open House, 1994 (Box 8)
    - Staff, Board Members, and Clinics, 1966-1976 (Box 8)
  - Videotapes
    - Womancare/Operation Rescue, March 16, 1989; VHS-C 1/2 in. videotape (Box 8)
    - "Peacocks" and "Deer" Advertisements, 1994; VHS videotape, approx. 1 minute, advertising Lansing and Jackson clinics (Box 8)
- Planned Parenthood of Southeast Michigan, 1999-2002
  Planned Parenthood of Southeast Michigan is a very small series containing materials dating before the merger with Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan. The series includes photographs from a 2002 legislative breakfast, and a 1999 video about clinic services.
  - "The State of the Community" Report, 2000 (Box 9)
  - Legislative Breakfast Photographs, 2002 (Box 9)
  - Videotape: "Choices: It's Your Choice,", 1999; VHS videotape, approx. 8 minutes (Box 9)
    (Produced by Planned Parenthood of Southeast Michigan)
- Planned Parenthood Association of Southwestern Michigan, 1969-1998
  The Planned Parenthood Association of Southwestern Michigan series consists primarily of scrapbooks and photographs. The scrapbooks contain clippings on Planned Parenthood clinics and services and related family planning issues, and date from 1969 to 1998, when the chapter merged with Planned Parenthood of Mid-Michigan. Photographs include images of staff, board members, and clinic facilities.
  - Annual Report, 1993 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1969-1979 (Box 9)
    - 1975-1979 (Box 9)
    - 1980-1986, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - 1986-1987, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - 1986-1990, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - 1989-1994 (Box 9)
    - 1995-1998 (Box 9)
    - Abortion, 1992 (Box 10)
    - Medicaid Abortion Ban, Proposal A, 1985-1989; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - "The Second Decade,", 1979-1989; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Photographs
    - Staff, Board Members, and Clinics, circa 1960s-1985 (Box 10)
Related Material
The library also has records of Planned Parenthood League, Inc. of Detroit. These records date from 1932 to 1979.